Guide to the Vine Deloria Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Subject Files, circa 1969-2003; Series III; 98.25; (88 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
  - Scrapbooks
    - Interviews: Custer Died for Your Sins (Box 124 Oversize)
    - Of Utmost Good Faith; Red Man in the New World Drama; God is Red; Behind the Trail of Broken Treaties (Box 125 Oversize)
    - Red Earth, White Lies, reviews (Box 125 Oversize)
    - Vine Deloria, Jr. Newspaper Interviews & Articles (Box 126 Oversize)
    - Vine Deloria, 1976-1987 (Box 126 Oversize)
    - Vine Deloria, 1988-97 (Box 127 Oversize)
    - We Talk, You Listen (Box 127 Oversize)
    - We Talk, You Listen, reviews (Box 127 Oversize)
  - Printed materials
    - Miscellaneous periodicals (Box 128)
    - Miscellaneous volumes (Box 129)
    - Red Earth White Lies poster (Box 130 Oversize)
    - Sioux Nation for Nixon headband (Box 130 Oversize)
    - Event posters (Box 130 Oversize)
    - National Book Festival posters, 2002 (Box 130 Oversize)
    - Three signed posters of Ghandi, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Albert Einstein, by Frank Szasz (Box 130 Oversize)
    - Chart, A Correlated History of Earth (Box 131 Broadside)
    - Map, Pleistocene Lakes in Nevada (Box 132 Broadside)
    - Poster, National Museum of the American Indian, Native Writers Series (Box 133 Broadside)
  - Clippings
    - Miscellaneous articles, conferences, re: Vine, 1991-2003, in lieu of scrapbooks (Box 134)
    - Miscellaneous items removed from Box 134., 1969-2001 (Box 135 Oversize)
      This box includes a charicature, bumper sticker, clippings, National Conference of Christians and Jews certificate of recognition, 1971, a 2001 calendar, and a t-shirt.
    - Miscellaneous reviews, etc., 1997-2002; VD & critique of Anthro.; IRA & Evolution; Duplicate reviews/articles; Escuela Tlatelolico; Jerelyn Lucero - artist - cover of Spirit's Reason (Box 136)
  - Card files
    - 4 boxes of index cards listing VD's library (Box 137)
    - 4 card file boxes: Claims cases; Supreme Court cases; Federal cases regarding American Indians; Federal Supplemental cases, Oklahoma state cases (Box 138)
    - 4 card file boxes: Federal Reporter Second Series; Legal and Political; Indians (Topics, Traditions, Medicine Men, Original World); American Indians (Box 139)
    - 4 card file boxes: Ethics and Phiosophy; Carl Jung; Philosophy and Science; Bibliography (Box 140)
    - 4 card file boxes: Religion; Evolution; Catastrophism - Dissenting material; Current research (soul book) (Box 141)
    - 4 card file boxes: Anthros (refuting orthodox doctrines); Psychology (near death experiences); Geomythology; Social Sciences (Box 142)
- Legal Files, circa 1992-2004; Series IV; 8.54; (9 boxes)
  Legal files are in rough alphabetic order based on box labels as received.
  The series consists of files relating to various Native American treaties, litigation against the Washington Redskins, and the Leonard Peltier/Wounded Knee case.
  - Treaties (Box 143)
  - Treaties (Box 144)
  - Treaties (Box 145)
  - Treaties (Box 146)
    Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services: Disk #4.
  - Treaties (Box 147)
  - Washington Redskins litigation, 1992-1996 (Box 148)
  - Washington Redskins litigation, 1998-2004 (Box 149)
  - Leonard Peltier - Consolidated Wounded Knee Case (Box 150)
  - Leonard Peltier - Consolidated Wounded Knee Case (Box 151)
- Teaching Files, Series V; 11.46; (10 boxes)
  The series consists of teaching files, lecture notes, course materials, and photocopies of readings for classes taught by Vine Deloria at the University of Colorado and the University of Arizona.
  Teaching files are arranged into three subseries: University of Colorado, University of Arizona, and readings. Within each box files are organized as received.
  - University of Colorado
    - CU lecture notes, Indian place names - states (Box 152)
    - Course materials (Box 153)
    - Course materials (Box 154)
    - Student and course materials (Box 155)
  - University of Arizona
    - Course materials (Box 156)
  - Readings
    Readings are arranged in rough alphabetic order by topic.
    Originally labelled "Xeroxed Books."
    - American Indians & Origins (Box 157)
    - Catastrophism - Floods - Psychic Phenomena (Box 158)
    - Jewish scripture, Yanktonai ethnohistory (Box 159)
    - Science - Philosophy, Ancient Technology, Labor History, Eastern Religions (Box 160)
    - Papers written by friends - Wilkins, Tinker, Patten, Walker, Masse, NARFies (Box 161)
- Organizational Records, 1973-1995; Series VI; 3.75; (3 boxes)
  The series consists of records from the American Indian Research Associates, Office of Education and the National Museum of the American Indian.
  Organizational records are arranged in rough alphabetic order. Within each box files are in the order in which they were recieved.
  - American Indian Research Associates, Office of Education files, circa 1973-1980 (Box 162)
  - National Museum of the American Indian records, circa 1977-1992 (Box 163)
  - National Museum of the American Indian records, 1989-1995 (Box 164)
- Awards and Tributes, 1970-2005; Series VII; 2.08; (6 boxes)
  Awards and tributes consists of honorary degrees, awards, tributes, and other honors bestowed upon Vine Deloria.
  - Tributes, 2004-2006 (Box 165)
    Also includes printed material.
  - Honorary degrees and awards, circa 1970-1996 (Box 166)
  - Awards and medals, 2001-2005 (Box 167)
  - Awards, 2004 (Box 168 Oversize)
  - Honorary degrees and awards, 1976, 1991, 2001 (Box 169 (Oversize))
  - District of Colorado attorney certificate, law school class photo, 1970 (Box 170 Oversize)
- Photographs, Series VIII; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Vine Deloria, playing guitar on stage at a concert (Box 171)
  - "Anyone urinating on the ground will be arrested" (Box 171)
- Audiovisual Materials, circa 1994-1996; Series IX; 1; (1 box); 19 VHS cassettes, 1 Betamax cassette, and 1 CD (Box 172)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Audiovisual materials consist of video cassetts with recordings of interviews with and presentations by Vine Deloria, documentaries, news programs, and conference recordings. Also includes an Ella Fitzgerald and Louis Armstrong CD, "Ella and Louis Again."
- Computer media, 0.21; (1 box)
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - MNI SOSE trailer one minute, 30 seconds Carol Burns Ironwood Films 913-262-4137, 2010-wa-39991-0001; 1 (Box 173)
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - MNI SOSE (RAW CUT) Ironwood Films Carol Burns, Dir. 913-262-4137, 2010-wa-39991-0002; 1 (Box 173)
  - CHAP 1. REP CHAP 2. REP CHAP 3. REP CH-BIB2. REP VINE DELORIA JR., 2010-wa-39991-0003; 1 (Box 173)
  - 15E, 20A, 20C, 21X, 21K, 21L, 2010-wa-39991-0004; 1 (Box 173)